Guide to the Raisa Berg Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Correspondence, 1941-2005
  - Subseries I.2: Correspondence with Organizations, 1975-2001
    - Stephan & Brady, Inc., Madison, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - United States Department of the Interior, 1991 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Universities
      - California Institute of Technology, 1978 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Chicago State University, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Evropeiskii Universitet v Sankt-Peterburge, 1996 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - George Mason University, 1985 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Harvard University, 1982 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Indiana University, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Johannes Gutenberg - Universtitat Mainz, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Karl Marx Universitat, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - North Carolina State University, 1975 1981 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Universitat Basel, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - Universite de Sherbrooke, undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - University of California, Berkely, 1981 1988 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - University of California, Davis, 1982 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - University of California, Los Angeles, 1991 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - University of Cambridge, 1986-1989 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - University of Connecticut, undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - University of Georgia, 1979 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - University of Missouri-St.Louis, 1985-1991 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - University of Pittsburgh, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - University of Sussex, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - University of Washington, 1982 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - University of Wisconsin, 1975-1986 (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - Vanderbilt University, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - Virginia Commonswealth University, 1993 (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - Washington University in St.Louis, 1983-1993 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - WARF Institute, Inc., 1975 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Wisconsin Veterans Museums, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Newsletters, bulletins, circular letters of various organizations, 1975-1981 (newsletters of South Florida Conference on Soviet Jewry see in Series III: Human Rights Activity--Newsletters: Box 51, Folder 2) (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Various, 1978-1984 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Outgoing, 1979-1982 (Box 26, Folder 13)
- Series II: Works and Writings by R.Berg; Research Data and Notes, 1937-2006
  The series comprises published and unpublished articles, monographs, papers presented at conferences and congresses, talks, memoirs, reviews, prose and poetry, essays, extensive research notes and data. Arranged in five subseries.
  - Subseries II.1: Scientific Writings and Works on the History of Science, 1937-2002
    Typescripts, manuscripts, and reprints of writings on Drosophila research, genetics and the history of genetics, general biology and the history of biology. Materials are arranged in several groups: articles and talks, lectures, dissertations, monographs and projects (organized alphabetically within each group); collection of works; reviews, forewords, abstracts, grant proposals, expeditions logbooks, experiments and research logbooks and data (organized chronologically within each group); tables, data, and notes related to various unidentified research and works, slides, photographs, and microfilms with research data and reference materials don't have formal organization.
    - Articles and Talks (published and unpublished; reprints, typescripts, manuscripts, notes; in English and Russian. See also collection of works in 3 volumes Genetika i evoliutsiia, Boxes 34-35))
      - "Analiz dinamiki mutatsionnogo protsessa v sviazi s izmeneniiami sredy obitaniia u cheloveka na primere chetyrekh form miopatii", 1972 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - "Dal'neishie issledovaniia po stabiliziruiushchemu otboru v evoliutsii tsvetka", 1957 (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - "Dominance of deleterious mutations in the populations of Drosophila Melanogaster", 1942 (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - "Ecological significance of correlation pleiades", 1960 (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - "Ekologicheskaia interpretatsiia korreliatsionnykh pleiad", 1959 (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - "Essigfliegen: indicator fur seuchen?", 1975 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - "Fliuktuatsii mutabil'nosti v populiatsiiakh drozofily i cheloveka", undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - "General evolutionary principle underlying the origin of developmental homeostasis", 1959 (Box 27, Folder 7)
      - "Genetic loadas a possible basis of inherent immunity in insects", undated (Box 27, Folder 8)
      - "Geneticheskii analiz dvukh prirodnykh populiatsii Drosophila melanogaster", 1941 (Box 27, Folder 9)
      - "Geneticheskii analiz populiatsii Drosophila melanogaster Delizhana (Armianskaia SSR)", 1944 (Box 27, Folder 10)
      - "High mutability and hybrid dysgenesis", 1982 (Box 27, Folder 11)
      - "Hybridization and selection as tools to reveal and to study the mode of action of mutator genes in natural populations of Drosophila", 1980s (Box 27, Folder 12)
      - "Inter- und intraspezifische Variabilitat der Flugeladerung in der Familie der Drosophilidae", 1962 (Box 27, Folder 13)
      - "Internal causes of environmental mutagenesis", undated (Box 27, Folder 14)
      - "Istoricheskoe razvitie mekhanizma realizatsii pola", 1942 (Box 27, Folder 15)
      - "K probleme povysheniia zimoustoichivosti segoletkov karpa, sazana i ikh gibridov", 1952 (Box 27, Folder 16)
      - "Korreliatsiia mezhdu mutabil'nost'iu i reguliatornoi sposobnost'iu organizma i ee evoliutsionnoe znachenie", 1945 (Box 27, Folder 17)
      - "Korreliatsionnye pleiady", undated (Box 27, Folder 18)
      - "Korreliatsionnye pleiady priznakov u Veronica Serpyllifolia L., V.Chamedrys L. i V.Krylovii Schischk", 1971 (Box 27, Folder 19)
      - "Korreliatsionnye pleiady u rastenii", 1961 (Box 27, Folder 20)
      - "Kuidas inimesest sai mikroobi mudel?", 1973 (Box 27, Folder 21)
      - "Lowering of the mutation rate as a result of intraspecific hybridization", 1941 (Box 27, Folder 22)
      - "Mesto teorii stabiliziruiushchego otbora I.I.Shmal'gauzena v sovremennykh evoliutsionnykh vozzreniiakh", undated (Box 27, Folder 23)
      - "Mutability changes in Drosophila melanogaster populations of Europe, Asia, and North America and probable mutability changes in human populations of the USSR", 1981-1982 (Box 27, Folder 24 to 25)
      - "Mutabil'nost' populiatsii Drosophila melanogaster, obitaiushchikh na granitse areala rasprostraneniia vida", 1942 (Box 27, Folder 26)
      - "Mutation rate in populations of Drosophila melanogaster inhabiting boundary areas of the species distribution", 1942 (Box 27, Folder 27)
      - "Mutator genes in population life and evolution and the membrane hypothesis of mutagenesis", 1990s (Box 28, Folder 1 to 5)
      - "Mutatsiia 'zheltaia' (yellow) v populiatsii Drosophila melanogaster g. Umani", 1961 (Box 28, Folder 6)
      - "Mutatsii steril'nosti u Drosophila melanogaster", 1938 (Box 28, Folder 7)
      - "Nasleduiutsia li priobretennye priznaki?", undated (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - "O nekotorykh mekhanizmakh, obespechivaiushchikh optimal'noe chislo naborov khromosom", 1963 (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - "O nekotorykh usloviiakh poiavleniia zhizni na Zemle", 1959 (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - "O putiakh evoliutsii genotipa", 1961 (Box 28, Folder 10)
      - "O vzaimootnoshenii mezhdu mutabil'nost'iu i otborom v prirodnykh populiatsiiakh Drosophila melanogaster", 1948 (Box 28, Folder 11)
      - "O zakonomernostiakh evoliutsii na primere kompleksnykh preobrazovanii priznakov pri divergentsii vidov veronik (Veronika L., Scrophulariaceae)", undated (Box 28, Folder 12)
      - "Observation on mutation rate fluctuation in man. Materials and methods", undated (Box 28, Folder 13)
      - "On mutations at the yellow and singed Loci in natural populations of Drosophila melanogaster", 1976 (Box 28, Folder 14)
      - "On populations of Drosophila melanogaster preserving different mutatition frequencies when transferred to identical conditions", 1942 (Box 28, Folder 15)
      - "On probable mutability fluctuations in human populations of the USSR paralleled by mutability fluctuations in Drosophila melanogaster populations", 1983 (Box 29, Folder 1 to 4)
      - "On the dynamics of the mutation process in man", 1974 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - "On the probable mutability changes in human populations of the USSR", undated (Box 29, Folder 6)
      - "On the sudden and synchronous rise of the abnormal abdomen phenotype in geographically isolated populations of the USSR", undated (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - "Otnositel'naia rol' mutatsionnogo protsessa i otbora v formirovanii fenotipicheskogo oblika populiatsii Drosophila melanogaster v sviazi s iavleniiami geneticheskoi nestabil'nosti", undated (Box 30, Folder 2)
      - Pis'mo uchastnikam konferentsii "Evoliutsiia vselennoi", 2002 (Box 30, Folder 3 to 4)
      - "Ponizhennaia chastota vozniknoveniia mutatsii pri vnutrividovoi gibridizatsii", 1941 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      - "Populiatsionno-geneticheskii podkhod k izucheniiu dinamiki mutatsionnogo protsessa na primere chetyrekh form miopatii", 1973 (Box 30, Folder 6)
      - "Probable mutability changes in human populations of the USSR and in Drosophila populations of Europe, Asia, and North America", undated (Box 30, Folder 7)
      - "Probable mutability fluctuations in human populations of the USSR, paralleled by mutability fluctuations in Drosophila melanogaster populations", undated (Box 30, Folder 8)
      - "Problema tselostnosti zhivykh system v trudakh I.I.Shmal'gauzena", 1966 (Box 30, Folder 9)
      - "Proiskhodit li eliminatsiia osobei geterozigotnykh po letal'nym mutatsiiam v estestvennykh populiatsiiakh Drosophila melanogaster?", 1943 (Box 30, Folder 10)
      - "Properties of ex eye, a mutant with extra eyes", undated (Box 30, Folder 11)
      - "Relative frequency of mutations in different chromosomes of drosophila melanogaster", 1937 (Box 30, Folder 12)
      - "Relative mutation frequencies in Drosophila chromosomes", 1934 (Box 30, Folder 13)
      - "Relative roles of stabilization and redifferentiation of the gene in the evolution of the hereditary substance", 1937 (Box 30, Folder 14)
      - "Restriction of P-element insertions at the notch locus of Drosophila melanogaster", 1987 (Box 30, Folder 15)
      - "Rol' malykh mutatsii v evoliutsii mutabil'nosti", 1941 (Box 30, Folder 16)
      - "Role of isolation in the evolution of dominance in natural populations of Drosophila melanogaster", 1942 (Box 30, Folder 17)
      - "Seminar po evoliutsionnym problemam v Botanicheskom institute im. V.L. Komarova AN SSSR", 1957 (Box 30, Folder 18)
      - "Sind mikroben fur degenerationserscheinungen verantwortlich?", 1974 (Box 30, Folder 19)
      - "Site-specific X-chromosome rearrangements from hybrid dysgenesis in Drosophila melanogaster", 1980 (Box 30, Folder 20)
      - "Sluchaina ili zakonomerna evoliutsiia", undated (Box 30, Folder 21)
      - "Sokhranenie razlichnoi mutabil'nosti populiatsiiami Drosophila melanogaster pri perenose ikh v odinakovye usloviia", 1942 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - "Sopostavlenie dinamiki mutatsionnogo protsessa u filogeneticheski otdalennykh form na primere drozofily i cheloveka", 1970 (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - "Sopostavlenie vnutrividovoi i mezhvidovoi izmenchivosti u veronik (rod Veronika)", 1973 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - "Soveshchanie po primeneniiu matematicheskikh metodov v biologii", 1958 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - "Spontaneous mutation process in geographically isolated populations of Drosophila melanogaster and its dependence upon hybridization", undated (Box 31, Folder 5)
      - "Struktura i razvitie", 1962 (Box 31, Folder 6)
      - "Studies in mutability in geographically isolated populations of Drosophila melanogaster during 1937-1941 1944-1947 and from 1957 until now", 1983 (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - "System der mutator-suppressor gene eine zukunstsanpassung bei Drosophila melanogaster", undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - "Tipy polimorfizma", 1957 (Box 31, Folder 9)
      - "Vid kak evoliutsioniruiushchaia sistema", 1944 (Box 31, Folder 10 to 14)
      - "Vse dorogi vedut k mikrobam", undated (Box 31, Folder 15)
      - "Zavisimoe var'irovanie mutabil'nosti i dominantnosti v predelakh odnoj estestvennoi populiatsii Drosophila melanogaster", 1944 (Box 31, Folder 16)
      - "Zavisimost' mezhdu mutabil'nost'iu i stepen'iu izoliatsii populiatsii Drosophila melanogaster", 1942 (Box 31, Folder 17)
      - "Zavisimost' mezhdu stepen'iu proiavlenii mutatsii v geterozigotnom sostoianii i ikh kontsentratsiei v genotype estestvennykh populiatsii Drosophila melanogaster", 1944 (Box 31, Folder 18)
      - "Znachenie izoliatsii dlia evoliutsii dominantnosti v estestvennykh populiatsiiakh Drosophila melanogaster", 1942 (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - Lectures
      - Manuscripts for lectures in Germany, undated (Box 31, Folder 20)
      - [History of Genetics]: syllabus, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 21)
      - "Teoriia evoliutsii" (syllabus), undated (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - Dissertations
      - "Nekotorye dannye k voprosu ob evoliutsii nasledstvennogo veshchestva", Leningrad, 1939 (typescript) (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - "Stabiliziruiushchij otbor v evoliutsii razmerov tsvetkov i semian travianistykh rastenii", Leningrad, 1964 (author's abstract, printed) (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Monographs and Projects:
      - Nasledstvennost' i nasledstvennye bolezni cheloveka. Leningrad: Nauka, 1971 (including review by V.Efroimson) (Box 32, Folder 3)
      - "On the history of Genetics in the Soviet Union", 1980s (typescripts, manuscripts, drafts):
        - "Fate of genetics in the USSR. A battle for intellectual freedom. Insight of a witness." (Box 32, Folder 4 to 6)
        - "On genetics in the Soviet Union" (Box 32, Folder 7 to 13)
        - "On genetics in the Soviet Union" (Box 33, Folder 1 to 5)
        - "On the history of genetics in the Soviet Union. Science and politics. The insight of a witness" (Box 33, Folder 6 to 12)
        - "Two types of intellectuals in Soviet Russia and their role in the history of genetics in the USSR" (Box 34, Folder 1 to 7)
    - Collection of works in 3 volumes Genetika i evoliutsiia, 2000
      - Foreword (Box 34, Folder 8)
      - Early articles (typescripts) (Box 34, Folder 9 to 12)
      - Works for 1st volume (typescripts, reprints, photocopies) (Box 34, Folder 13 to 16)
      - List of works for 2nd volume (Box 35, Folder 1)
      - Works for various volumes (Box 35, Folder 2 to 3)
      - List of corrections (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - Petition to the Soros Foundation for funding (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - Letters of recommendation and reviews addressed to the Soros Foundation (signed by Aleksandr Ginzburg, V.V.Babkov, V.K.Shumnyi) (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Reviews, 1973-1996 (Box 35, Folder 7 to 11)
    - Foreword to Mekhanizmy biologicheskoi konkurentsii, 1964 (Box 35, Folder 12)
    - Abstracts, 1940s-1990s
      - 1940s-1960s (Box 35, Folder 13)
      - 1970s (Box 35, Folder 14)
      - 1980s (Box 35, Folder 15)
      - 1990s (Box 35, Folder 16)
      - Undated (Box 35, Folder 17)
    - Grant proposals and reports, 1970s-1990s (including related correspondence. See also Series I--Subseries I.2: Correspondence with Organizations)
      - 1970s-1980s (Box 35, Folder 18 to 25)
      - 1990s (Box 36, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Undated (Box 36, Folder 6 to 9)
    - Expeditions Logbooks, Experiments and Research Logbooks and Data:
      - 1973-1974 Ararat, Dilizhan, Magarach (Box 36, Folder 10 to 13)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 37, Folder 1 to 3)
      - 1977 (Box 37, Folder 4 to 7)
      - 1978 (Box 38, Folder 1 to 3)
      - 1979 (Box 38, Folder 4)
      - 1980 (Box 38, Folder 5)
      - 1983 (Box 38, Folder 6)
      - 1984 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - 1985 (Box 39, Folder 2 to 3)
      - 1988 (Box 40, Folder 1 to 2)
      - 1991 (Box 40, Folder 3)
      - 1993 Fialki (Box 40, Folder 4)
      - Undated (Box 40, Folder 5 to 9)
    - Tables, data, and notes related to various unidentified research and works, various dates (Box 41, Folder 1 to 15)
    - Slides, photographs, and microfilms with research data and reference materials (including 6 microfilm reels) (Box 42, Folder 1 to 26)
  - Subseries II.2: Memoirs, 1980s-1990s
    Manuscripts and typescripts of R. Berg's memoirs Sukhovei, its English translation Acquired Traits; Zolotye rytsari v strane sotsializma, and memoir note on Iosif Brodskii. There are also reviews on published memoirs and related materials.
    - Sukhovei (Russian):
      - Manuscript, pp. 357-716 (Box 43, Folder 1 to 14)
      - Foreword, afterword, list of illustrations (Box 44, Folder 1 to 3)
      - Loose parts (Box 44, Folder 4 to 8)
      - Drafts, corrections, related materials (Box 44, Folder 9 to 12)
      - Reviews, 1983-1985 (Box 44, Folder 13)
    - Acquired Traits (English translation of Sukhovei):
      - Typescript, pp. 1-174 (Box 44, Folder 14 to 17)
      - Loose parts and pages (Box 44, Folder 18 to 19)
      - Reviews, 1987-1990 (Box 44, Folder 20)
    - Zolotye rytsari v strane sotsializma:
      - Manuscript, pp.1-253 (Box 45, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Typescript, pp.1-200 (Box 45, Folder 6)
      - Related materials (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - Memoir note on Iosif Brodskii, undated (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Subseries II.3: Essays about Various People and on Popular Science; Publicistic Works, 1950s-2006
    Published and unpublished articles and essays; radioscripts; reprints, typescripts, manuscripts, notes; related research materials. Arranged in few groups: personalia, popular science, publicistic works. Contains Manuscripts, typescripts, reprints, andclippings. See also Subseries II.1--Collection of works in 3 volumes Genetika i evoliutsiia: Box 34, Folders 8-16
    - Personalia (essays, articles, and research materials about various persons. Manuscripts, typescripts, reprints, clippings):
      - Astaurov, Boris: (Box 46, Folder 1)
        - "Life and research of Boris L. Astaurov", 1979 (Box 46, Folder 1)
      - Avetisian, Minas:
        - "Minas Avetisian - Esenin armianskogo sela", 1989 (Box 46, Folder 2)
        - "Tragicheskaia sud'ba Minasa Avetisiana", 1988 (Box 46, Folder 2)
      - Berg, Lev Semenovich:
        - [Berg about Berg], undated (Box 46, Folder 3)
        - "Ekspeditsiia L.S.Berga na ozero Balkhash", 1955 (Box 46, Folder 4)
        - "Iz istorii ekspeditsionnykh issledovanii L.S.Berga", 1950s (Box 46, Folder 5)
        - "Na ostrovakh Aral'skogo moria", 1954 (Box 46, Folder 6)
        - Script for BBC, undated (Box 46, Folder 7)
        - "Zapiski ob ottse", 2000 (Box 46, Folder 8)
        - Notes and related materials (Box 46, Folder 9)
      - Delone, Vadim:
        - "Vadim Delone i ego kniga", undated (Box 46, Folder 10)
        - "Vadim Delone, sinii gusar dvadtsatogo veka", undated (Box 46, Folder 11)
        - About Vadim Delone by other authors (clippings), 1985-1998 (Box 46, Folder 12)
      - Egiaian, Gregor:
        - "V poiskakh Gregora Egiaiana", 1988 (Box 46, Folder 13)
      - Ignatov, P.G.:
        - "Teletskaia ekspeditsiia P.G.Ignatova 1901 g.", 1957 (Box 46, Folder 14)
      - Lichkov, Boris Leonidovich:
        - Biographical essay for Dictionaire du Darwinisme, 1996 (Box 46, Folder 15)
      - Liubishchev, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich:
        - Biographical essay for Dictionaire du Darwinisme, 1996 (Box 46, Folder 16 to 17)
      - Poliakov, Lev: (Folder 1)
        - "Lirika i satira L'va Poliakova", 1988 (Box 47, Folder 1)
        - Notes, album of his photographs, related materials (Box 47, Folder 1)
      - Sakharov, Andrei Dmitrievich:
        - "Moi vstrechi s Sakharovym", 1997 (Box 47, Folder 2)
        - "O Sakharove", 1996 (script for BBC) (Box 47, Folder 2)
      - Shmal'gauzen, Ivan Ivanovich:
        - "Ivan Ivanovich Shmal'gauzen", undated (Russian, English, French) (Box 47, Folder 3 to 6)
        - "Raboty Ivana Ivanovicha Shmal'gauzena po embriologii pozvonochnykh I ego teoriia stabiliziruiushchego otbora", undated (Box 47, Folder 7)
      - Timofeev-Resovskii, Nikolai Vladimirovich:
        - Endless defense, 1992 (letter to editors) (Box 47, Folder 8)
        - "In defense of Timofeev-Ressovsky", 1990 (Box 47, Folder 9 to 12)
        - "Nikolai Vladimirovich Timofeev-Resovskii", undated (Box 47, Folder 13)
        - "Nikolai Vladimirovich Timofeev-Resovskii", 1981 (obituary) (Box 47, Folder 14)
        - "N.V.Timofeev-Resovsky did not collaborate with the Nazis", 1991 (Box 47, Folder 15 to 16)
        - "Nikolai Vladimirovich Timofeev-Resovskii - obitatel' dvukh mirov", 1988 (Box 47, Folder 17 to 19)
        - "V zashchitu N.V.Timofeeva-Resovskogo", 1990 (Box 48, Folder 1)
        - "Why does Muller-Hill accuse Timofeev-Resovsky?", 1988 (Box 48, Folder 2)
        - Research and related materials (Box 48, Folder 3)
      - Tsvetaeva, Marina:
        - "Moia Tsvetaeva", undated (Box 48, Folder 4)
      - Vernadskii, Vladimir Ivanovich:
        - "V.I.Vernadskii. Sotsial'nye prognozy i zabluzhdeniia", undated (Box 48, Folder 5)
        - [Vernadskii], manuscript, undated (Box 48, Folder 6 to 9)
        - [Vernadskii], script for BBC, 1993 (Box 48, Folder 10)
        - "Vernadskii. Osushchestvivshiesia prognozy i zabluzhdeniia", 2006 (Box 48, Folder 11)
        - "Vernadskij", biographical essay for Dictionaire du Darwinisme, undated (Box 48, Folder 12)
        - Drafts (Box 48, Folder 13 to 15)
        - Research and related materials (Box 48, Folder 16 to 17)
      - Volodin, Boris Genrikhovich, undated (Box 48, Folder 18)
    - Popular Science: (Box 49, Folder 1 to 9)
      - "Khudozhestvennye zhanry natury", undated (Box 49, Folder 1)
      - "Kordebalet spiashchikh mukh", 1990s (Box 49, Folder 1)
      - "Povest' o genetike", 1980 (Box 49, Folder 2)
      - "Vremia i prostranstvo zhizni", undated (Box 49, Folder 3 to 6)
      - "Yeast, raisins, bombs and fruit flies", 1980 (Box 49, Folder 7)
      - "Zakonomerna li evoliutsiia, ili Pochemu kuritsa ne revnuet", undated (Box 49, Folder 8)
      - Scripts for BBC, 1990s (Box 49, Folder 9)
    - Publicistic Works:
      - "K semidesiatiletiiu publikatsii stat'i Stalina 'Golovokruzhenie ot uspekhov' 2 marta 1930 goda v gazete 'Pravda'", 2000 (Box 49, Folder 10)
      - "Moi monozigoticheskii bliznets", undated (Box 49, Folder 11)
      - "Ostorozhnyi polulegal Daniil Granin", 1988 (Box 49, Folder 12)
      - "Regenerating capitalism…", undated (Box 49, Folder 13)
      - "Sravnitel'nyi analiz elementarnykh sredstv vyrazheniia raznykh vidov iskusstv", 1963 (Box 49, Folder 14 to 15)
      - "Stikhiino-informatsionnyi rynok Sovetskogo Soiuza, ego istoki i vzaimootnosheniia s sotsialisticheskoi ekonomikoi v tselom", undated (Box 49, Folder 16)
      - "Zemel'naia reforma Stalina i kul't ego lichnosti", undated (Box 49, Folder 17)
  - Subseries II.4: Prose and Poetry, 1940s-1990s
    Manuscripts and typescripts of Berg's original prose and poetry of various years.
    - Prose (manuscripts):
      - "Skazki antimira", 1960s-1970s (Box 50, Folder 1 to 4)
      - "Ulybka sapozhnika", 1950s-1990s (short stories) (Box 50, Folder 5 to 6)
      - "Velikoe i smeshnoe", undated (short stories, incomplete) (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Poetry of various years, 1940s-1990s (English, Russian. Manuscripts, typescripts). See also: "To James F.Crow commemorating his birthday and his return from La Yolla", 1979 (poem, holograph manuscript) in Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Crow (Box 3, Folder 16) and "To Professor Sewall Wright on the occasion of his 89th birthday" (poem, holograph manuscript) in Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Wright (Box 20, Folder 9) (Box 50, Folder 8 to 10)
  - Subseries II.5: Fragments, extracts, notes, and loose pages from various unidentified works, various dates